The sort method sorts a list.
I will change the reverse statement to a sort,
rerun the code, and we will see that the list
is now in alphabetical order.
Before we go any further, I want to cover
another basic programming concept with you.
You may notice that every method we have used
so far has parentheses.
Basically, every method in every programming
language has parentheses because methods can
contain arguments, meaning settings, or items
that are being manipulated.
Take this sort method.
There are no arguments yet, so we have the
default sort, which is in ascending order.
However, I can add an argument, reverse=True,
inside the parentheses.
Remember, Boolean values start with a capital
letter.
I will rerun the code, and we see the list
of cities in reverse order.
One aspect of this code we have yet to work
with is the list of populations on line 5.
These populations coincide with these cities.
We want to know the largest population among
these cities and the smallest population among
these cities.
The max and min functions identify those values,
respectively.
I will add a print statement on line 10 to
print the max of the population variable.
I will run the code, and we see that among
the populations, 1.6 million is the largest
value, again representing the max function.
I will change the max to min, rerun the code,
and we will see the smallest population of
32000, again referencing the populations variable
and the min function.
The last list operation we will cover is the
length of a list.
As people collect items in games, there may
come a time when we need to display how many
items they have collected.
The len method displays the length of a list.
I will add a print statement on line 11 to
print the length of the capitals list.
The code is print(len(capitals)).
In rerunning the code, the length is three,
as we have three capital cities in the list.
We have reached the end of data type operations,
so let’s do a little analysis exercise for
a code block.
I will open the 126-analyze file, and we have
a quote and a type of list.
Use the second part of the Review 1.2 exercise
in the project workbook to determine what
this print statement will return, and if this
statement will work, and then we will review
this code and reveal the answers.